你们想没想过火箭入轨精度为什么那么高
Have you ever wondered, how do real-world rocket vehicles get to orbit with such an accuracy,
能和速度近每秒8公里的空间站交会对接?
that they meet and dock with a space station traveling at almost eight kilometers per second?
长懒不看版答案: 这需要箭载计算机上高深的算法
The short answer is: through some very ingenious algorithms in their onboard computers.
细说的话 我叫Przemek
For the long answer: my name is Przemek,
欢迎观看航天飞机制导算法在坎巴拉太空计划中的实现
and this is Space Shuttle guidance done in Kerbal Space Program.
假设我们要给空间站送快递
So let's say we want to deliver some supplies to the International Space Station.
大家之前也玩过KSP
Now, you've flown those missions before in Kerbal Space Program,
知道如果发射后进入的轨道比较好 交会对接就会很轻松
and you know it's not so very hard to rendezvous, once we're in a good orbit.
但如果你初始轨道和目标轨道有倾角 那就不好办了
But if your initial orbit is inclined to your target, things get pretty complicated.
所以这类发射中最重要、最难的部分就是进入停泊轨道这一步
So the most difficult and important part of such launch is the ascent to parking orbit.
所以我为此专门设计了一套上升段的自动驾驶程序
And I have created an ascent autopilot that does exactly that.
使用kOS编写
It was programmed in kOS
这MOD是坠吼的 不知道的话欢迎去试试
(one of the best mods out there, so do look it up if you don't know it already)
它使用航天飞机的算法来进行入轨制导
and it uses the Space Shuttle's algorithm for orbital guidance.
我的代码非常灵活 适用于很多其他火箭
My implementation is flexible enough that we can run other vehicles too,
而这个视频里我将使用 "Real Scale Boosters" MOD里的Atlas V进行演示
so to demonstrate, I'll use the Atlas V from Real Scale Boosters mod.
使用我的自动驾驶程序进行这样的发射任务 只需选定目标
Now, using my autopilot, flying such missions is as easy as select target,
然后输入 "run PEGAS"
and run PEGAS.
程序一开始会计算发射窗口
And the first thing that happens is calculation of the launch window.
实际上只是一个粗略估计
In fact, it's just a rough estimate,
因为即使在现实中也很难精确计算
because in reality it's very difficult to calculate it precisely,
所以我们只做粗略估计即可
but we'll make do with that.
因为整个代码不需要发射窗口计算有多精确
Fortunately the whole system is fairly insensitive to that
前后差一两分钟问题不大
and being off by a minute or two shouldn't be a big issue.
现在开始 火箭的姿态和分级就完全交由PEGAS控制了
From this point, our vehicle is in complete control of PEGAS
which handles staging and attitude.
倒计时!
So, we have the final countdown,
RD-180发动机点火!
there should be the RD-180 ignition,
AJ-60固推点火! 起飞!
and now the AJ-60s and liftoff!
发射分两个阶段
Now, there are usually two phases of ascent to orbit:
首先是大气层内的上升段
and the first one, we're in now - atmospheric ascent.
这时候不用多精确 飞得稳你就成功了
And the idea here is not so much about precision of what we're doing, as is about safety.
这时候主要目标是让你的火箭能完整的飞出大气层
We just want to get outside the atmosphere in one piece
而不是被迎面而来的大风(动压)吹散架了
instead of breaking up due to high dynamic loads.
程序在这里的逻辑就是遵循FAR的教程
So the logic we're following
is taken pretty much straight from ferram's Realism Overhaul tutorial,
先转一定的角度 然后姿态上保持零攻角一直飞就好
so basically pitch over by some known angle
and hold attitude prograde at zero angle of attack.
等我们飞到大气足够稀薄的地方 动压小了
And once we've gained enough altitude that air density is no longer an issue,
就要切换到发射入轨的航天飞机制导算法了
then we will switch to orbital ascent using the Space Shuttle algorithm.
即PEG 全称"动力显式制导"
If you ever heard the word PEG or Powered Explicit Guidance,
then this is exactly it, this is one way of referring to it.
另外有一点 包括航天飞机在内 绝大多数轨道制导算法
Now, the thing about most orbital guidance algorithms, Shuttle's included,
并不考虑大气层的存在
is that they do not take atmosphere into account at all.
我给自己留了个台阶 毕竟我真不清楚最先进的算法是啥样的
Although take that with a grain of salt, as I don't know about the most modern algorithms.
因为空气动力学背后的数学真的非常复杂
This is because maths behind aerodynamics are very complex
在当时那个年代 很难在飞行中实时解算出结果
and back then it couldn't be quickly and reliably solved mid-flight.
所以大气层内的阶段 由于主要目标是省油和大致的准确
So, because in that phase the only thing that matters is precision and fuel efficiency,
所以我们只要等它飞出大气层 空气动力学效应可以忽略就好
we're better off waiting till we're above the air, so we can neglect its effects.
现在固推差不多该烧完了
And right about now the SRBs should be flaming out,
我们等一会再抛固推
and we're going to jettison them a little later.
现实中Atlas V也是这样做的 火箭会带着烧完的固推再飞几秒
This is actually what the real Atlas does, it carries them for a few seconds,
因为空气可能还没那么稀薄 扔太早不安全
as it might be unsafe to separate if we're too low and the air is too dense,
所以我们让火箭再飞一会
so we carry them for a little bit.
现在自动制导程序激活 接管火箭姿态控制
And now the automatic guidance will engage and take control of attitude.
但是谁钦点这算法叫"航天飞机制导算法"的?
But why the Space Shuttle? And why the Shuttle's guidance algorithm?
它有什么特别的吗?
And what's so special about it?
想回答这个问题 我们得先回到六十年代末
Well, to understand that we need to go back in time to late 1960s
当时航天飞机还没有出现
when the Shuttle doesn't exist yet -
只停留在图纸与一堆需求提案中
not beyond drawing boards, proposals and requirements.
当时有两大特别的需求
And two of those requirements are of particular interest to us right now.
一个是新飞船要能在轨建造并维护空间站
The first one was the ability of the newly designed vehicle
to allow construction and servicing of a low orbit space station,
也就是后来家喻户晓的国际空间站
which will be later known as the International Space Station.
另一个需求是除了能发射卫星外 还要能把卫星从轨道上带回来
The other was the ability to retrieve satellites from orbit and not just deliver them.
这两点需求有个共同点
Both those objectives have one thing in common:
都需要有能力进行在轨交会
they share a mission profile of an orbital rendezvous.
当然这倒不是什么新的操作
This isn't to say that rendezvous was something new,
这些东西在之前的双子星座计划就演示过了 阿波罗计划里也玩烂了
as the concept was demonstrated in the Gemini program before and used extensively in Apollo.
只是这从来没像这样放进火箭设计的常规需求里
Just never before has this kind of mission profile been a routine one.
因此 航天飞机需要一个全新的制导系统
So for this reason, among others, the Shuttle needed an entirely new guidance algorithm.
于是在70年代初
And indeed, in the early 70s,
德雷伯实验室设计出了"统一动力飞行制导"算法
the Unified Powered Flight Guidance was designed by the Draper laboratory.
"统一"是因为这个系统是为很多飞行模式设计的
It was called "unified" because it was a single program to handle many kinds of flight modes:
包括发射 在轨机动中止 离轨点火等等
ascent, abort through orbital maneuvers, up to deorbit burn.
当然在我的程序中我只实现了标准的发射模式
Out of those I only implement the standard ascent mode in my autopilot,
过会我会详细解释
and I will describe it in a bit more detail in a moment,
因为现在我们要改变发动机工作模式了
because now we're approaching a burn mode change.
之前发动机为全推力工作状态
Previously the engine was set at full throttle,
但如果继续保持地板油 我们会很快达到8G的过载
but if we continued on like that, we'd soon reach acceleration in excess of 8 Gs -
这对载荷很不好
which isn't good for the payload at all.
所以发动机会慢慢收油门 保持4.5G的过载
So we're going to throttle down gradually to limit acceleration at about 4.5 Gs.
航天飞机会限制在3G来保护宇航员们
The Shuttle itself had a 3 G limit in place to protect the crew.
接下来是发射时序中另一个事件:
And another set of pre-timed events occurs now:
先是整流罩分离
we first jettison the payload fairing
然后是半人马火箭整流罩载荷支撑装置分离
and now the Centaur Fairing Load Reactor.
接下来是发动机关机 准备分离
And now we have engine cutoff and a separation sequence,
这一切都是由PEGAS控制的 全部可自定义
which is controlled by PEGAS, and fully customizable.
首先是一级助推分离 然后半人马上面级沉底发动机启动
First the Common Core Booster separates, then ullage motors activate on the Centaur,
然后点火 UPFG再次接管火箭姿态
and there's the ignition, and UPFG soon after takes control of the attitude again.
看看效果如何 看起来轨道一切正常
So let's see how we're doing: the orbit looks pretty good,
程序报告还要飞400秒
and the algorithm reports time to go of about 400 seconds
差不多够我解释UPFG的基本法则了
which will be just about enough time to explain the basic principle behind UPFG.
但在回答"怎么做"之前 我们先回答"做什么" 即火箭制导的中心思想
But before we focus on "how" let's answer "what" it really does - the very idea of rocket guidance.
大致思路为 一枚已知的火箭
As a general principle, we want to steer a known vehicle
其状态已知 要进入一个目标状态
which has a known current state into some target state
对于发射模式来说 目标就是某条轨道
which in the ascent mode happens to be some kind of orbit.
现在轨道一般是用一组轨道根数来描述的
Now, this orbit is most likely described with a set of orbital elements
比如半长轴 偏心率 或者是有些人偏好的近地点 远地点
such as semi-major axis and eccentricity or apoapse and periapse if you prefer,
还有倾角 升交点赤经
and inclination and longitude of ascending node.
但这些数值很难处理
It's very uncomfortable however -
如果你只想改变远地点
if you've ever tried changing just your apoapse,
那你必须得先飞到近地点才行
you know it's impossible unless you're currently at periapse.
改变倾角得在升交点赤经也同理
Similar thing with inclination and LAN -
想只改变一个参数而不碰其他值太难了 这对制导算法来说很不友好
it's hard to change one without the other, which isn't good for guidance at all.
而在理想情况下 我们想在某个直观的 比如平面直角坐标系下处理数据
Ideally, we'd like to work with some mathematically sane coordinate system,
like Cartesian XYZ system.
在直角坐标系里描述当前状态还算简单 但描述目标轨道就不一样了
In XYZ it's fairly easy to describe our current state, but it's not the same with a target orbit.
毕竟轨道不是一个点 而是一整条椭圆
After all, orbit is not a single point but a whole ellipse of them,
所以用这样的坐标系描述椭圆也不太现实
so such description is not really possible.
但如果我们已知XYZ坐标和速度
However if we were given some XYZ position and velocity,
那就很容易判断当前轨道是否达标
we could easily verify whether it is a good orbit or not -
只需要一一核对高度 速度 角度之类的就行了
simply by checking altitude velocity angle and the like.
其实这样已经足够我们去进行精确制导了
And it turns out, this is enough to do very precise guidance.
剩下就是火箭本身了 你要知道自己该去调整哪些参数
One remaining thing is the vehicle - after all, we need to know exactly what are we steering.
我们可以总结出很多火箭的参数
In general, there will be plenty of parameters we could write down about it,
但对于火箭的运动 只有四个参数是有用的
but from the point of view of rocket motion, it all boils down to just four:
火箭干重 剩余燃料重量
dry mass of the vehicle, mass of the propellant it has in the tanks
以及发动机参数 即推力与比冲
and parameters of its engines: combined thrust and specific impulse.
简言之就是重量 推力 推力效率(比冲)
So basically, how much does it weigh,
how hard can it push itself and how efficiently can it do that.
对于多级火箭 每一级都会有相应的四组数据
And if we have a multi-stage vehicle, there will be those four numbers per each stage -
这会导致很难把它们套进数学公式
which in turn isn't so very comfortable to plug into any mathematical equation.
于是设计制导系统的大佬们又发明了推力积分
So the clever guys from guidance came up with something called thrust integrals.
就不在这细讲了 怕大家睡着
I will not give a detailed explanation of them here, as this would be unnecessarily boring,
只是说这个方法给我们带来了很大的便利
just outline the greatest advantage they give us.
推力积分让我们能够合并火箭的各级参数
The thrust integrals allow us to coalesce the vehicle description into one set of numbers,
不用去管火箭的分级数量
irregardless of the number of stages.
因此 多亏了推力积分 让算法也能对多级火箭进行制导了
So, thanks to that, the capability to guide multistage vehicles
is kind of built into the algorithm itself.
虽然航天飞机其实并没有占到多少便宜
Even though the Shuttle did not really make full use of that,
因为航天飞机主要部分仍是单级的
for the major part it was a single stage vehicle,
它的OMS发动机只是用来圆轨
the OMS thrusters were used only to circularize.
至此我向大家解释了UPFG的第一个要点:And it just so happens that I've explained the first important part of UPFG:
推力积分的计算
calculation of the thrust integrals.
我们先总结一下目前我们知道的内容
So let's recap what have we found out so far.
我们知道我们在控制的火箭本身参数如何 知道我们在哪
We know what vehicle we're steering, we know where we are,
但我们不知道我们要去哪
we don't know where we want to be.
但我们有办法知道我们的目标(如果存在的话)是否达标
But we have a way of figuring out whether our destination - if we had one - is a good one.
我们基本上不知道我们要去哪里这件事听起来好像怪怪的
The fact that we essentially don't know where we're going might seem like a bit of a problem,
但我们不妨先假设我们以某种方式猜到了确切目标
but let's assume for now that we somehow guessed the exact destination.
我们已知当前XYZ位置和速度矢量
We have some XYZ position and velocity vector.
可以计算还差多少距离 还差多少速度
From that we could calculate the distance we need to cover and the velocity we need to gain.
即视频左侧窗口中PEGAS界面的"Vgo"
This is exactly this velocity-to-go, the v-go marker that you see in PEGAS interface.
可以看成是你还需要多少速度增量
It can be thought of as maneuver delta-v which you're used to.
而我们火箭参数已知 所以还能计算出获取这些速度还要多少时间
Knowing our vehicle, we can also calculate how long will it take to gain that velocity,
对应左侧窗口中的"Tgo"
and this is the time to go - the t-go - marker.
接下来引入航天飞机使用多年的一个技术
Now, there is a technique, known for years prior to the Shuttle,
可以让航天飞机直接根据当前状态与目标状态计算俯仰偏航角
that allows directly calculating pitch and yaw angles, given the current and target states.
即"线性正切制导律" (LTG)
This is called Linear Tangent Guidance,
这也是我们最开始需要用到推力积分的原因
and it's the main reason we needed those trust integrals to begin with.
它只有一个中心思想:
It only has one catch:
数学上 通用的重力与推力解法类似于空气动力学 难度大
since general solution for gravity and thrust is mathematically difficult, just like aerodynamics,
所以LTG假设地球是平的 重力矢量恒不变
the LTG assumes the Earth is flat, and the gravity vector never changes.
这个假设显然是不对的 所以结算的结果肯定也不对
Which is obviously wrong, so our result will be wrong
因为现实中地球是圆的 重力方向也会变
because in reality, the spherical Earth's gravity will pull us down differently.
所以设计UPFG的人想到一个绝妙的办法来修正
So the guys who designed UPFG came up with a neat way to correct that.
他们设计一个函数来预测火箭未来只受重力作用下的状态
They designed a function to predict the future state of a vehicle in free motion under just gravity,
称为"圆锥曲线状态外推"
called Conic State Extrapolation,
然后想办法把推力带进去
and then figured out a way to incorporate thrust into it.
这样就有了一个精度尚可的未来状态推断
This way, they ended up with a decent future state predictor,
利用这两个工具 我们可以先用线性正切制导律粗略计算
using which we can: first calculate a rough guidance using Linear Tangent,
然后使用圆锥曲线状态外推计算考虑重力矢量的实际情况
then use Conic State Extrapolation to find out what the gravity vector really would be like,
将得到的结果重新进行一轮计算
and save that knowledge for the next run.
带回LTG中 逐渐提高计算结果的精度
Plug it back into the LTG, gradually increasing the accuracy of its results.
而实际上 最开始的误差可能不只是对重力处理上的误差
But in fact, the initial inaccuracy might not be only due to bad gravity handling.
我们可能连目标状态都猜错了 但这些也能被修正过来
We simply might have guessed our target wrong - would be good to correct for that too.
所以UPFG并不是慢慢调整我们初始的预测值
And the way UPFG approaches that is not by slowly correcting our initial guess.
而是直接拿最接近解算出的结果作为新的目标
Instead it finds an entirely new target position, that is nearest to the predicted one,
抛弃之前的全部预测值
and discards our guess at all in the process.
拿最新的预测值 再跑一遍整个算法
And with this new target, the whole algorithm runs again.
最后总结一下 我们先猜测一个我们的目标值
So, to sum up: we start by guessing some destination,
利用线性正切制导律计算俯仰偏航角
we calculate pitch and yaw angles to get there using Linear Tangent,
然后用圆锥曲线状态外推修正重力
we use Conic State to correct for the gravity,
得到一个新的预测值 验证我们之前的预测是否准确
and we verify our guess in the target by picking a new one.
不准就拿新的预测值重新跑一遍算法
And then we run the algorithm again with that new value.
重复几次 误差就会越来越小
And if we repeat this process several times, the error will get smaller and smaller as we go,
小到最终无限接近真实结果
and at some point it will become so little,
这时就可以说解算完成了 误差已经解决掉啦
that we might safely say that a true solution has been found - one that has no errors anymore.
此时称为"算法收敛"
And when that happens, we say that the algorithm has converged.
由此就可以遵循制导系统运行了
From then on we can follow its guidance.
就是这样 希望我给大家描绘出了航天飞机制导算法的大致轮廓
So there you have it, I hope I have at least outlined the Space Shuttle guidance algorithm.
当然我没有讲得很深
Of course, I didn't go into much detail
因为这里面的数学非常复杂 十分钟远远讲不完
as this would be very complex and definitely not just for a 10 minute video.
但你想要了解更多内容的话 欢迎查看视频详情部分
But if you want to know more, do check the description for this one.
我在我的GitHub页面上对我的算法进行了详细的解释
I've written a much more thorough explanation of the algorithm on my github pages.
因此 如果你对UPFG的各种错综复杂的问题感兴趣
So if you're interested in the all intricacies and bells and whistles of UPFG,
那请务必去看看
then please do check it out.
刚好现在主发动机快关机了
And right about now we're getting to the the main engine cutoff,
应该几秒后就是了
which should be in a few seconds.
有啦~
And there we have it.
PEGAS告诉我们任务完成啦 我们看一下轨道参数
PEGAS says mission successful so let's take a look at the parameters:
倾角和升交点赤经看上去很完美
inclination and longitude of ascending node look perfect,
与目标轨道角度相差0度
angle between orbits: 0 degrees.
远地点近地点可能差一点点
Apoapse and periapse might look a little bit off,
但我个人觉得已经在Atlas V火箭的精度内了
but I think, not sure, but I think they are within actual accuracy limits of the Atlas V vehicle.
然后我们看看从这个停泊轨道到在轨交会的点火难度如何
But let's see how difficult would it be to plan a transfer maneuver from this parking orbit,
如果我们想变轨与空间站交会的话
if we wanted to rendezvous with the Space Station.
需要提高远地点 与目标轨道相切
So if we just raise our apoapse till we get a little intersect...
像这样
just like that...
然后调整一下点火时间 在几圈后进行 应该差不多就……
and now if we do that a little later, a few orbits later, then we should probably be
就接近了
getting close.
我看看
Let's check that out.
交会情况应该不错
We should get a pretty reasonable intersect.
有了! 200米
Oh, there we have it - 200 meters.
我大概只用了十秒就拉出来一个200米交会的机动 怎么样?
200 meters intersect by a maneuver I planned within what, 10 seconds?
那么就这样吧
Well, that's it,
希望大家喜欢本期视频
I hope you've enjoyed watching it,
如果你想亲自测试PEGAS算法
if you want to test PEGAS yourself,
欢迎去视频详情的链接里下载
the links are in the description so you can download it right away.
教程都在里面 大家可以自己试试 可能有点痛苦
Tutorials are included so you can try it yourself with hopefully little pain.
再次感谢大家的观看 我是Przemek
Once again, thanks for watching, my name is Przemek,
感谢大家观看航天飞机制导算法在KSP中的实现
and that was Space Shuttle guidance algorithm done in Kerbal Space Program.
祝大家射得准!
Fly accurately!